HOMER'S ODYSSEY
Cinematic rendering of the greatest
poem of ancient Greek literature
Costumes from the tailorshops
of the Scala Theatre in Milan.
Scenes after old drawings that are
in the famous Brera library (Milan).
The adventures of Ulysses
after the poem by Homer
THE ODYSSEY
The departure of Ulysses
Ulysses says goodbye to his wife
Penelope, his son Telemachus,
his old father Laertes,
...and leaves Ithaka, to go
to the war against Troy.
The ships of Ulysses leave Ithaca
Believing Ulysses to be dead,
the suitors take possession
of his house...
...and demand that Penelope
choose a new husband among them.
Penelope manages to put off the choice
of the new husband as long as until she
will have finished weaving the shroud.
At night she undoes the stitches.
Caught by the suitors doing this,
she promises to complete the work.
After the destruction of Troy,
Ulysses sets sail with his
companions to return home.
Ulysses lands on the island
of the cyclope Polyphemus.
Polyphemus devours one
of Ulysses' companions.
Ulysses blinds the
terrible Polyphemus.
Ulysses flees from Polyphemus
with the surviving companions.
Ulysses flees with his companions
from the cave of Polyphemus,
letting the sheep carry them.
After the stolen sheep have been
brought on the ships, Ulysses pushes
away from land with his companions.
Ulysses mocks Polyphemus
from the ships.
Polyphemus hurls a rock
at Ulysses' ship and begs
for Neptune's revenge.
To escape the seductive call of
the sirens, Ulysses blocks the
ears of his companions with wax,
...and has himself tied
to the mast of the ship.
During the passage through the
strait of Scylla and Charybdis...
...Ulysses' ship looses six more
companions, whom the monster eats.
Ulysses lands in Sicily,
where the sacred bulls
of Jupiter are located.
End of the first part.
A short break in order to
prepare the second part.
Ulysses, who removed himself from
his companions, is called back
by the smoke of burning bulls.
Aching with hunger, despite his
warnings, Ulysses' companions feed
on the meat of the sacred bulls.
Jupiter delivers the lightning on
Ulysses' ship to avenge himself.
Only Ulysses saves himself...
...and reaches the
island of Calypso.
Where he spends seven years.
Calypso, by will of the gods,
advises Ulysses to build
a raft to return home.
Ulysses goes to work.
After a moving farewell, Ulysses
leaves the island of Calypso.
To avenge Polyphemus, the seagod
Neptune steers the ship to sea.
Saved by a miracle,
Ulysses goes ashore at
the mouth of a stream.
Nausicaa, the daughter of
the Phaeacian king Alcinous,
welcomes Ulysses,
...gives him clothes,
and advises him that
he head for her father.
Ulysses heads for the
palace of the king.
After a cordial reception
he recounts his adventures.
...he is given precious presents.
The ship of Alcinous
finally takes Ulysses
back to his homeland.
The sleeping Ulysses
is brought ashore.
End of the second reel.
One moment please to
prepare the second part.
The goddess Minerva changes Ulysses
into an old beggar, so that he
isn't recognized by the suitors.
Ulysses heads for the hut of
the old shepherd Eumaeus. Here he
also finds his son Telemachus.
Minerva orders Ulysses to reveal
himself to his son Telemachus.
With help from Minerva,
Telemachus recognizes his father.
The suitors maltreat the beggar.
Loathly Ulysses observes
the flirtations of his
maids with the suitors.
Ulysses hides with his son
Telemachus the suitors' weapons.
Penelope declares to wish to marry
he among the suitors who is capable
to string the bow of Ulysses.
Ulysses watches the inability of the
suitors at stringing his bow, and
now has his bow handed to himself.
Ulysses starts a massacre
among the suitors.
Finally Penelope recognizes
the husband and embraces him.
The end.